Guide to the Records of the New York University College of Dentistry 1550 B.C.E.-2000 (Bulk 1850-1950) RG 25
New York University Archives
The Records of the New York University College of Dentistry
Bulk, 1850-1950
1550-2000
RG 25
New York University Archives
24.0 paige boxes 24 boxes
The New York College of Dentistry was founded in 1865 with thirty-one students and ten faculty members. In 1925, the College merged with New York University and developed into a leading center for dental care, research and policy. This collection allows the viewer to understand the School’s development through a series of student notebooks and administrative files from the late 1800s and early 1900s. It also contains a wide array of antique dental tools.
New York University. College of Dentistry.
Arrangement
General Administration folders are filed by subject and arranged according to the year of the earliest document. Manuscript collections are arranged in chronological order and student materials are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into three series:
Series I: General Administration
Series II: Memorabilia
Series III: Student Records
Separated Material
Promotional Materials, Bulletins, Annual Reports, Publications, Commencement Records, Audio/Video Materials, and Photographs were incorporated into the general NYU Archives collection.
Scope and Content Note
The contents of the Records of the New York University College of Dentistry include adminstrative records, student report cards amd notebooks, and a large collection of dental paraphernelia. The latter has been grouped in the series 'memorabilia', and includes dental tools (many from the nineteenth century), model teeth, medallions, pins, and a 16th century dental tool said to have been owned by John Steinbeck.
Historical/Biographical Note
The New York College of Dentistry was established in 1865 in a small rental space on Twenty-Second Street and Fifth Avenue. The mission of the College was to promote altruism in dentistry while providing first-rate education. Upon its inception, the school had thirty-one students and ten faculty members. Of the original thirty-one, the first graduating class contained nine students.
When the New York College of Dentistry merged with New York University in 1925, it became known as the New York University College of Dentistry. With the similar philosophies of the two institutions, the merge led to the creation of a dental school at the forefront of research and postdoctoral education.
Today, the College of Dentistry has approximately 1,600 students from across the world. About fifty percent of the student body is female and fifty percent minority. The greater aim of the College is to improve the health of underserved populations, and more generally, to improve health worldwide. The College of Dentistry is also home to the John and Bertha E. Waldmann Memorial Library, which holds more than 38,000 bound volumes and subscribes to 442 professional journals.
The New York University College of Dentistry offers D.D.S., B.S. and A.A.S. degrees. It is now the third oldest and the largest private dental school in the United States.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the Archives with specific questions regarding access to such records.
Provenance
Transferred to the University Archives by the Waldman Library of the New York University College of Dentistry in August, 2003.
New York University. College of Dentistry.; Dental instruments and apparatus.; Dentistry |x Study and teaching.
- Series I: Correspondence.
  - Accreditation, Kriser Dental Center Waldmann Dental Library, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Act of Incorporation of NYCD, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between NYU and NYCD, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book of Contacts, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Centennial Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centennial History, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clinical Fee Schedules, 1977, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clinic book, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clinics, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean’s Memoranda, 1960-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dean Edward G. Kaufman Memoranda, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department of Preventive Dentistry and Community Health, Dental Health Organizations, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Educational Standards, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faculty, Lectures in Physiology, Professor Stein, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty, Meeting Minutes, 1898-1915 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Faculty, Progress Examinations, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Faculty, Progress Examinations, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, Records, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty, Records, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty, Records, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty, Records, 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty, Records, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty, Records, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gifts/Donations, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Investigation into Theft, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Henry Dodge Record of Operations, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Henry Dodge Day Book, 1851-1852 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Murray and Leone Guggenheim Foundation for Dental Research, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, 0000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Parent Agreement for Minors, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Parent Agreement for Minors, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Peridontia Corresponding Group, Bulletin 1- 25, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Registration, Applications, A-C, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Registration, Applications, D-Z, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1890-1891 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Student Record Book, 1898-1906 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Student Records, Expelled Students, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Student Records, Non-attending Students, 1895-1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Student Records, Qualifying Certificates, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Student Records, Signature Book for Diplomas, 1897-1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1865-1897 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1904-1913 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1914-1925 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trustees Roster, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Undergraduate Preventative Dentistry Variety Show, 1968-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series II: Memorabilia
  - Medallions (10), 0000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Paperweights (3), 0000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 19th Century Dental Tools (100+), 1800-1900 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Teeth, Model and Actual, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Powders (7), 0000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Small Metal Tools (10), 0000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Moldings (2), 0000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Model Teeth (8), 0000 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Model Teeth, 0000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Tools (20), 0000 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Film Reel, 0000 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dental tool given to Dr. Waldman by John Steinbeck from 1500 B.C.E. (approximately), 0000 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Metal Plates (2), 0000 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Plaques (6), 0000 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Post Extracter, 0000 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Film, 0000 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Condyles (27), 0000 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Pins (6), 0000 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Gysi Trubyte Articulator, 0000 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Tools (28), 0000 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Shells (5), 0000 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Facebow, 0000 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Antique Instruments (25), Gift from Erum Kaplam, 0000 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Stamps, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Atomizer, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Model Teeth, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Molten Metal Endo File, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Reame Sterilizer, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Dyes, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Paper Disks, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Protractor, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Cloth Strips, 0000 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Antique Dental Instruments (15), 0000 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Plaques, 0000 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Saklad Nameplate, 0000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Centennial Certificate, 0000 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Framed Faculty Photos (7), 0000 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin R. Hoch Dental Toolkit with Tools, 0000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - NYU Banners (2), 0000 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Antique Dental Tools (20+) with Descriptions, 0000 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - X-rays (2), 0000 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Records (3), 0000 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Dr. J. Van Chandler Dental Toolkit with Tools, 0000 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Saklad Nameplate, 0000 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Framed Certificates (3), 0000 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Antique Dental Toolkit and Tools, 0000 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Series III: Student Records
  - College of Dentistry Admission Cards, 1889-1907 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, D-K, First Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, A-Z, Third Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, Third Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, First Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, A-H, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, H-P, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, P-W, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, A-V, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, S-Z, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, 1915-1916 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Student Report Cards, A-E, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, E-K, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, K-Z, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, A-M, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, M-P, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, P-R, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Student Report Cards, M-R, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Student Report Cards, R-S, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Student Report Cards, S-W, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Student Report Cards, W-Z, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Student Report Cards, A-H, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Student Report Cards, H-P, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Student Report Cards, P-Z, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Student Report Cards, A-F, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Student Report Cards, G-L, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Student Report Cards, S-W, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1919 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Anesthesia, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Anatomy, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Chemical Lab, 1925 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Chemistry, Second and Third Year, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Diseases and General Surgery of the Mouth, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Student Lecture Notes, General Pathology, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Hypnosis, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Materia Medica, Second Year, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Materia Medica, Third Year, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Operative Dentistry, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Student Lecture Notes, George Kaplan, Oral Surgery, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Oral Case Recording, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Oral Case Recording, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Abraham Gralnick, Orthodontia, 0000 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Orthodontia, 0000 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Physiology, 0000 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Physiology Lab, 1920 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Prosthetic Dentistry, Second and Third Year, 0000 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Jacob Louis Blass, 1929 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Jankelson, 0000 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Student Lecture Notes, 0000 (Box 24, Folder 7)